Chapter 3

"Repeat exactly the wordss of my emisssary. They have been chossen carefully to allow no trickss of wording, and I advise you follow this example in any future dealings in this tongue."

The boy who stood before the moonlit snake cocked his head to one side, as if he were himself imitating the motions of the snake. "Musst I ssweear to thiss now?"

And, from the snake, the hiss of dry laughter.

"You wissh to try your cunning against my own, boy? I do appreciate cunning in my desscendantss, even if I may dissapprove of the impulssess towardss which it iss directed. This Chamber will not refuse you for any passt attemptss to bypasss thiss precaution, you may try ass you wissh to deceive it; but you may not enter until you have ssworn."

The boy smiled faintly. "How very generouss of you. Iss that truly wisse, though?"

Again the hiss of snakish laughter.

"To give each Heir free rein to attack my defenssess? Perhapss not. But then, I did not ssay it would be precissely free."

A faint hiss. "And what do you mean by that?"

"There iss a price, boy, to trying the wardss upon my Chamber. My emisssary knows the time you first spoke to it, it will notice any excesssive delay. And the Monsster that waitss within for you knowss also, and the longer you delay and plot againsst me the lesss knowledge you will find within the Chamber for yoursself, when you finally enter." A faint smile. "Might be wisser, boy, to ssimply take the lore that iss offered, rather than wasste ssome in hopess of denying future Heirss. But if you think yoursself able to bypasss the wardss of Ssalazar Sslytherin upon thiss moment, then by all meanss make the attempt."

Harry felt a faint sickness in the pit of his stomach, as he watched through the Penseive, watching the game between Salazar and the Dark Lord. Salazar had been cunning indeed - perhaps more cunning than Harry was himself. His game was being played at a level Harry had never even thought of.

And he had already seen that it wasn't going to be enough to hold back Lord Voldemort.

Harry wanted to give up, right then, wanted to put down the Penseive and run from the room, but he needed to know, he needed to know, what this other Tom Riddle had done here.

So he watched, stood behind the eyes of that other version of himself as the boy stood before the silver snake and thought.

And a voice came from behind him.

"Close your eyes."

He obeyed instantly, for he recognized that voice. It was his own.

"Good. Slytherin's Monster is a Basilisk. That should be all you need to know."

Footsteps moving across a stone floor as that other Riddle walked to stand before the Patronus.

"I currently intend no actionss towardss the Chamber of Ssecretss or towardss anything I might find there that could in any way harm the ability of the Chamber to convey its ssecretss to ssubssequent Heirss of Sslytherin, and I do not anticipate my intentionss changing at any point in the future."

A snakish hiss, and his eyes opened again.

To claim victory or to admit defeat, he had six hours.

The boy was pacing through the halls of Hogwarts, deep in thought. His hand moved unconsciously, tapping against his leg, his face, his opposing arm.

And behind him, not in truth but in memory, walked another of himself, a Tom Riddle from forty years in the future, thinking the same thoughts.

The flaw in the oath had been clear enough. Perhaps it had even been intentional, since Salazar hadn't wanted to deny Heirs access to the Chamber entirely based on a single failed attempt (though that was looking increasingly foolish of him). But, whatever the reason, it made no statement about past actions, only about future ones. And that meant that, whatever plans he might make now, whatever actions he might take, no matter what they were, they would not interfere with his ability to make the promise in Parseltongue later. (Or, rather, earlier. He hadn't gone back in time yet, he was planning to do so as near to the end of his six hours as possible, just in case he thought of something in the interim that required the use of his Time-Turner.)

And yet, that didn't seem to be enough. Even if he somehow thought of a way to kill Slytherin's Monster right now (which didn't seem like it would be easy, given that he was a first-year student and it was a fearsome monster, and that he didn't even know how to find it at this point), all that would accomplish was denying the lore of Slytherin to himself as well. He needed to find a way to be able to kill it later, and yet he also needed to be able to honestly intend not to kill it later.

Four feet pacing back and forth in a hallway, two of them real and two of them memory, as those two Riddles walked and thought.

When his future self had spoken to him, it had identified Slytherin's Monster as a Basilisk, as if that fact specifically was important, as if it were some specific property of the Basilisk that would let his plan work.

He already knew the lore of the Basilisk - it was an obvious thing for a seeker of the Chamber of Secrets to learn - and he knew its weakness. The crowing of the rooster was fatal to the basilisk, however odd that might seem in a monster born from a chicken's egg.

(Neither Riddle knew that this had been an intentional feature. When Herpo the Foul had first bred Basilisks, he had been concerned that his creations might escape, might use the intelligence he had bestowed upon them to breed themselves, capturing chickens and toads and hatching more and more Basilisks, and so he had wrought a very specific weakness into them to prevent this. Herpo had thought himself very clever to take such a precaution, until the day the witch Evaine Alexander had invented the Chicken-Chucking-Charm.)

If you genuinely believed you would honor the promise, you would be able to give it in Parseltongue, even if you were wrong. If you could somehow trick yourself into thinking you wouldn't harm the Monster - but if a perfect Occlumens couldn't lie in Parseltongue, simple trickery wouldn't do.

A Confundus Charm or Legilimency might work, and False Memory Charms almost certainly would. He couldn't cast those himself, but maybe he could find an upper-year boy who owed him a favor, there were plenty of those by now, like the one he'd gotten to cast a Patronus and then leave, he'd need to get someone else to Obliviate them afterwards if he didn't want them to know, it would be tricky but should be doable...

...if he weren't in Hogwarts, where the use of any of those things on a student by anyone other than a Professor would instantly alert the Headmaster. And, while the Headmaster and the Professors did like him (well, most of them did), they didn't like him that much.

What had the exact wording of the oath been again? "I currently intend..."

The first Riddle paused in the hallway, his feet stopping where they were.

Then he was running, his feet pounding on the floors.

"I realize it's unusual, Headmaster, it's just..."

"Out of the question, I'm afraid." The words were stern, but Headmaster Dippett's voice was soft. "I realize Hogwarts is like a home to you, Tom, but Hogwarts policy clearly states that students should return to their regular dwellings over the summer except in the greatest extremity."

"So...there's nothing you can do then, Headmaster?" The voice of Tom Riddle was soft, wavering, sounding almost on the verge of tears, and Harry watched from behind him with a kind of sickened fascination, knowing he was seeing a master at work.

"I'm afraid not, Tom." Dippett paused. "Is there some reason you're asking?"

"N-no, no reason." The mask Riddle was wearing seemed to choke slightly, and there were tears gathering in the edges of his eyes. "I'm s-sorry, I shouldn't have asked. Th-thank you for your time, Headmaster."

The boy turned to go, and a hand on his shoulder brought him to a halt. He turned, and Headmaster Dippet's brown eyes stared into his own.

"Tom..." Halting, the words were, as if the Headmaster wasn't sure what to say. "Have...have they been treating you well? At the orphanage, I mean?"

The mask widened its eyes a bit, as if faintly panicked. "W-what? N-n-no, they've been p-perfectly kind. N-nothing to worry about." Each line a work of art, the pathetic, obvious lie of a panicked eleven-year old, one that could be seen through on the instant by any adult, while behind the mask the Dark Lord stood, watching and listening.

"I see." Sad now was the Headmaster's voice. "Well, Tom, I'm sure we can work something out..."

And, when it was over, no-one but that second Riddle saw the first one take off the mask and smile.

"You have learned well these passt yearss, Heir. It iss now time for me to bid you farewell. There is one final message I must bear you from Ssalazar Sslytherin, one favor he sseekss from you."

The boy's eyes were steady.

"Go forth and change thiss world. Whether you sseek good or ill matterss little. Too often we choosse neither path, too often we forssake both the path of good and the path of evil, to follow the path of whatever sseemss eassiesst at the time. You, the Heir of Sslytherin - we do not bid you choosse good over evil, but we do bid you choosse."

A slight nod. "I will. Thiss I sswear."

"And remember thiss: the Chamber of Ssecretss musst now remain clossed until the next Heir of Sslytherin sshould arrive to claim it."

And the Dark Lord smiled, and raised his hand.

Upon that hand there was a slim golden ring, and set into that ring there was a small diamond.

"What iss that?"

The Dark Lord did not answer. He slid the ring gently off his finger, bent down and laid it on the ground by the coils of Slytherin's Monster. The great serpent bent down, sniffed at it.

"A ring? What iss thiss?"

"For ssix yearss I bore it, all for thiss moment. I give it to you now, and bid you farewell."

And the Transfiguration Tom Riddle had placed upon that ring six years ago, that he had maintained for six years without pause, Transfiguring into the stablest form he knew in order to minimize the internal changes it would suffer over time, staying at Hogwarts over the summer in order to avoid detection by the Ministry's Trace, began at last to unravel.

For Salazar's oath required you to swear that you intended no action that might harm the Monster. But if you could find an attack on the Monster that could be triggered, not by action, but by the lack of an action...

The creature that appeared could be called an bird only in the loosest sense of the word. Six years of Transfiguration had taken a heavy toll, even in a form so stable as a diamond. The eyes were glassy and dull, the feathers mottled with blood, one leg would not bear its weight and it slumped against the floor.

But its throat was still nearly as strong as when it had been caught, frozen at the very instant of crowing, and as it died it managed to complete that act.

Harry rose from the Pensieve, gasped in deep breaths of air. It hadn't answered all his questions, there were still things he didn't know. Where had the body of the Monster gone, say? Destroying it with Fiendfyre or the Reductor Curse might or might not count as violating the oath - though if Voldemort hadn't planned to destroy the Monster's body, if the idea had come to him later, the oath wouldn't have bound him - but it wasn't mission-critical to know. Wherever the body had gone, the important thing was that there wasn't anything left here. Professor Quirrell might have been lying about the specifics of how it was done, but the general concept of 'nothing of value left in the Chamber of Secrets' had been true.

There had to have been other steps, too, he hadn't actually seen six hours of memories. Somehow Riddle must have figured out that Slytherin's Monster was a Basilisk in that time - though, to be honest, it seemed like that was pretty common knowledge - so that he could pass that information back to himself as a hint. Or maybe he would have figured it out anyway, and the stable time loop was one where he gave himself a hint to figure it out faster, like when Harry had gotten his Time-Turner; he still wasn't quite sure how that worked. The young Riddle had probably talked to the Transfiguration Professor too, to figure out what exactly he ought to do, unless for some reason he too had been given a rock from his father earlier in the year...but, again, that didn't seem particularly important.

The last few hours had been - well, Harry wouldn't say wasted, anything he could learn about that other Tom Riddle was potentially valuable, but suboptimally spent. One part of him was making remarks along the lines of I told you so, but Harry wasn't listening. He rose to his feet to leave...

And a hissing voice came from behind him.

"Well, thiss iss unexpected."

Chapter 4

"Well, thiss iss unexpected."

Harry whirled around at the sound of the voice behind him, then squeaked at an embarrassingly high pitch and fell over.

Just behind him was a giant serpent, coiled around the room, its head lowered towards the ground.

Harry's mouth was still making involuntary noises, and the only words he could force out were somewhat incoherent. "What...but...how...but...what?"

"Sspeak to me, Heir of Sslytherin. How did you come to be here?"

Oh, that was right, Basilisks would only be able to speak in Parseltongue, that had even been in Fantastic Beasts and Where to Find Them, it wasn't even uncommon knowledge.

"I sspoke to a ssnake Patronuss that referred to itsself as the emisssary of Sslyth-"

A sharp hiss cut him off. "I know the meanss by which thiss Chamber may be accesssed. But I did not expect any Heir to arrive so soon. The lasst Heir of Sslytherin came to Hogwarts a mere few decadess ago, there has not been time for another to arisse."

The snake raised its head, a pose that Harry instinctively parsed as threatening, like a dog showing its teeth. "And I arrive to find that the lasst Heir was ssomehow both cunning enough to sslay Sslytherin'ss Monsster and foolissh enough to leave a messsage gloating about it. But more than that, I arrive to find another Heir. An Heir who sshould not be here, who sshould not even exisst."

The coils shifted position, slid over and around one another, and Harry saw poised, ready to pounce, attack stance. "The next thought would, of coursse, be that you are ssomehow connected to the previous Heir. A creation of hiss, or a ssimulacrum, ssent here in an attempt to finissh the Chamber. And if there iss one time we may sstrike againsst an Heir, it iss when the continuation of the Chamber iss threatened. If there iss a good explanation for your pressence here, would be wisse to sspeak now."

Harry gulped, then the words came flooding out. Honesty might or might not be a good general policy, but when you were speaking to a snake that could kill you literally with a blink, you were incapable of lying, and the snake thought you were the Dark Lord come back to somehow finish it off (though how it had escaped Lord Voldemort the first time was still beyond him), Harry couldn't see any better ones.

"There iss a good explanation. It iss ssomewhat complicated, pleasse allow me to finissh explaining before eating me." Harry winced. He'd wanted to phrase that a bit differently, but somehow it hadn't worked. It seemed Parseltongue prevented even small lies for the sake of politics.

But he hadn't been eaten yet, so that was encouraging.

Harry spoke.

The snake listened.

It asked questions.

Harry answered them.

At length, Slytherin's Monster spoke.

"That iss...the ssingle leasst plaussible sstory I have ever heard."

Harry's heart sank, he wondered if he could reach for his wand, what would happen, how fast could the Monster kill him...

"But...I have heard it in Parsseltongue. And it iss not wisse to be hassty to judgement in ssuch circumsstances. Sso...Heir, you will casst the Anti-Confunduss Charm upon yoursself, now."

"I do not know what that iss."

An exasperated hiss. "Sspell iss not difficult to casst, sshould be within power even of firsst-year child. Gessturess and incantationss required are tricky, but if you have any chance of truly being Heir you sshould be able to learn them sswiftly. Follow my insstructionss precissely."

It took Harry three tries, but at length he was able to manage a Nullus Confundio, and the black beam touched him and winked out.

There was an expectant silence, and Harry realized that there was something he ought to be saying.

"All that I have ssaid to you before, regarding my connection with the Dark Lord and my purpossess in being here, iss true."

This repeated with a couple other spells Harry didn't recognize. He listened, learned, and cast them almost on autopilot, while his brain worked in the background.

Perhaps the Dark Lord had failed to kill Slytherin's Monster - but it had seemed pretty decisively killed. Maybe it could come back to life, like a phoenix? No, that would be stupid, how would it even do that. Or maybe...

Harry was pretty confident now, he thought that he knew what had happened. If you could create a Basilisk, teach it lore, and set it in Hogwarts to teach your descendants...

..then why couldn't you create two?

Or three? Or ten? Or, in fact, a whole population of Basilisks, living in a Chamber more secret still, breeding when necessary enough to survive even a maximal attrition rate of one per Heir, passing the lore to one another to ensure its survival...

One part of Harry's mind was coming up with arguments against this, and another was shooting them down. Basilisks didn't breed, they were born from chicken eggs hatched beneath toads...so you have populations of chickens and toads down there too, and have the Basilisks hatch new ones. The crowing of the rooster is fatal to a Basilisk...so you place a permanent Quieting Charm over the area where the chickens are kept. These Basilisks will need to eat something...so you take whatever your plan was for feeding one Basilisk for hundreds of years, and multiply it by ten.

Some side part of Harry noticed that he was no longer being taught spells. He looked up, and saw Slytherin's Monster rocking back and forth, a pose Harry identified as thought.

"I cannot tesst for the pressence of Falsse Memory Charmss, but the length and detailss of the memoriess you have desscribed to me could not feassibly be created...my nature makess it imposssible to examine you for Legilimency, but that would not be enough to fool Ssalazar's cursse, no more than a perfect Occlumenss could.."

And the serpent bowed its head, and some part of Harry said respect.

"From what you have told me, it ssoundss that your time here is very limited. Given that, I sshall teach you what I can during thiss time, ssave only that, for the ssake of thiss Chamber, nothing sshall be revealed about how I ssurvived the Dark Lord'ss attack."

"Thank you, but I have no idea what I sshould be learning." Whether Harry was right or not about how this serpent had survived the Dark Lord's attack (that is, it had survived by not being here, and a different one of Slytherin's Monsters had died instead), it didn't seem like a good idea to ask. "Need to attain, ssomehow, power ssufficient to defeat Dark Lord before he..."

The Basilisk was laughing, a series of short sharp hisses. "Foolisshnesss."

"What?"

"Many lesssonss are left here by Ssalazar. Let thiss be the firsst, and heed it well, child. Sslytherinss may turn to evil far more often than any other Houssess, and yet we are far lesss dangerouss when we do."

Harry's confusion must have shown on his face, for the monster continued.

"Sshould a Gryffindor fall to darknesss, they will not be sstopped. Nothing sshort of their death will turn a true Gryffindor asside from their tassk, even if their tassk is an evil one. But a Sslytherin? To turn asside a Dark Lord of Sslytherin, you need not defeat him; you need only provide him with ssome incentive."

That...that was actually a really good point.

In the Muggle world Harry came from, a sufficiently rich, famous or powerful person could commit almost any crime and get away with it. Judges and juries would bend over backwards for them, prosecutors would settle out of court. And, in the worst case, they could find some reasonably nice country with no US extradition, and go hide out there.

And yet, somehow, billionaires very rarely committed murders, even though if they killed someone and then jumped on the next plane to Dubai they would almost certainly get away with it.

To keep a billionaire from murdering people, you didn't need to defeat him - you didn't need to prevent him from committing the murder, or from escaping afterwards. You just needed to incentivize him not to commit the murder, to make committing it not his best course of action. Oh, a reasonably competent billionaire could kill someone and then get away; but he would need to leave the country, away from his massive mansion and his five-star chef and his social circle, and go live in another country, and he didn't want to do that.

And Harry didn't need to defeat Quirrell, he just needed to give Quirrell some incentive not to do evil things.

That was it, that was the problem. That was why Quirrell was such a terrifying Dark Lord. It wasn't just that he was the most powerful wizard alive, with a vicious cruelty and a Dark creativity. The Muggle world had people like that too, and most of them wound up being socially neutral at worst.

It was that he was so powerful that the wizarding world could not impose incentive schemes on him. 'You have nothing to threaten me with and nothing to offer me'.

Harry had some things he could imagine offering the Dark Lord, but they all seemed like bad ideas. Offering to give the Dark Lord even more power, in exchange for doing less evil with it...Harry wasn't even comfortable calling that Plan B, it needed a letter more like P or X.

But in that case...

And Harry looked up at the Monster. "What can you teach me of Transsfigurationss?"

A flickering of the tongue that somehow managed to convey the dry sarcasm Harry more normally associated with Professor Quirrell. "Of coursse. Transsfigurations."

"What?"

"Lissten to me, young Heir, mark my wordss well. I bear another messsage from Ssalazar. When firsst an Heir sspeakss to me, I am to ssee which magicss they sseek to learn, and sspeak to them bassed on that."

"If an Heir sseekss only ssimple sspells, trivialitiess of old timess, I am to leave them the reminder that ritualss can work far greater magicss, and direct them to ssome ssacrificial ritualss that are ssimple, ssafe, ssacrifice very little, and yet produce effectss beyond the reach of their magicss."

Harry fought back a laugh as he remembered a conversation he'd had once with Neville.

"To thosse who sseek immediately the mosst powerful ritualss and the Darkesst lore, I am to leave a warning that thesse ritualss are dangerouss beyond what they expect, and certain ssuggesstionss ass to when it iss truly necesssary to perform a ritual and when ssimpler magicss will ssuffice. To thosse who assk me of time, who sseek to ravel the ssecretss of Atlantiss and of Time-Turnerss, I am to leave insstructionss on how experimentss may ssafely be performed without rissking the dissassters that can occur when you Messs With Time."

"And to thosse who immediately assk of Transsfiguration, I am to leave a single word."

"Beware."

He should, perhaps, have been paying more attention to the warning, but instead Harry's mind realized something else.

If you were wizardborn, Mr. Potter, you would know to take it seriously, when a powerful magus tells you only to beware.

Professor Quirrell had said that, and that was what had finally tipped Harry into realizing.

Speaking to Slytherin's Monster was almost exactly like speaking to Professor Quirrell.

And it was obvious why.

Quirrell had spent seven years in Hogwarts, surrounded by idiots as he put it, with exactly one being he'd consider reasonably intelligent to talk to. He'd spent seven years speaking to his Basilisk, learning from it, acquiring mannerisms and patterns of thought from it, perhaps the closest thing he'd had to friendship during those days...

And yet he had still killed Slytherin's Monster.

Some part of Harry had been making excuses for Quirrell, reminding Harry of all the times he'd felt contempt towards idiots. But when Harry had found someone who actually seemed sentient, someone who could actually think for herself, someone who could run alongside him, who could match her mind with his own, he would never have dreamed of killing her, the idea would simply never have crossed his mind.

But that just seemed to be the way Quirrell's mind operated. If you were intelligent enough to be worth talking to, you were intelligent enough to be a threat, and if you were intelligent enough to be a threat the way to deal with you was to kill you. Any meaningful relationship Quirrell could have, he would expect to be temporary, to end violently in the defeat of one side or the other.

Harry didn't understand it, didn't understand why, didn't understand how someone could think that way, but he knew, now, knew with a dawning certainty, that he was going to oppose Lord Voldemort, for those two different spirits could not exist in the same world.

And he thought he knew how he would go about it, too.

Chapter 7

Tell me, Professor...have you ever played Morrowind?

Harry hadn't played the game himself until after he already knew the trick, so he hadn't gotten to figure it out for himself, but he knew how it worked.

There was a skill you could use, called Alchemy. Your character could learn to brew potions with magical effects, and the power of these effects was determined (as it would be in any self-respecting magic system) by your character's Intelligence attribute.

But one of the types of potions you could brew was a Fortify Attribute potion, which would temporarily raise one of your attributes.

Like, say, Intelligence.

And then, with your newly increased Intelligence, you could brew a more powerful Fortify Intelligence potion that would boost your intelligence still further.

And further.

And further.

At first the effect would be small, that was the way exponential progressions worked. But it would get faster, and faster. If each step increased your intelligence by 10%, after ten steps your Intelligence would be two-and-a-half times what it had been before. After twenty steps it would be more than six times what it had been before. After one hundred steps it would be more than thirteen thousand times what it had been before.

So part of Harry's mind had always been on the lookout for a way to replicate this using the magic that he had found actually existed.

And for so long, he hadn't seen it. For the problem with deontological constraints is that if you never genuinely consider the arguments for violating them, you never truly know whether you should. And Harry had dutifully recited the Rules of Transfiguration in each of Professor McGonnagal's classes, and chastised himself for his reckless experimentation, and stepped carefully around all the useful parts of Transfiguration without thinking about it.

Until Professor Quirrell taught him that lesson.

Holding the Philosopher's Stone would allow you to perform human Transfiguration, would let you safely Transfigure yourself without dying of Transfiguration sickness.

But there were other times you could perform human Transfiguration as well, and that was what Professor Quirrell had done.

If you were confident that you would obtain the Philosopher's Stone in the next few hours...then you could use Transfiguration to your heart's content, Transfigure yourself or anyone else as you wished, and then once you obtained the Philosopher's Stone use it to prevent their death.

It was what Professor Quirrell had done to his student hostages.

And another time you could use human Transfiguration on yourself was if you were going to die anyway, or if you were willing to die for something, and you could accept that you would die when the Transfiguration wore off.

Slytherin's Monster had taught him a way you could Transfigure yourself to enhance the power of your muscles, pouring the power of your magic into them to enhance your body...

But his magic was a part of him in the same way his muscles were, there was something in his body that dictated his magic, dictated how powerful it would be and what effects he could achieve, and he could approach that with the same mechanic. It had taken him most of his week, with the reluctant assistance of Slytherin's Monster and a bunch of rats that had been subjected to what might have been the least ethical series of experiments ever performed, but he had learned how to do it.

And once he knew what to do, knew how to Transfigure himself to increase his magical power, he could do it again, and again, and again.

If there were no limits to the power of your magic, what would you do, if you could do anything?

But this power would not last. You couldn't maintain a Transfiguration on something as large as a human indefinitely, however powerful you were. If the Dark Lord accepted his offer, one condition he'd like to add to it would be access to a Philosopher's Stone, to keep Harry from dying in the next few hours. (Hufflepuff was asking him if he really thought he deserved to live given what he was about to do. Gryffindor was asking if it was worth the effort of negotiating for that, if it would be better to sacrifice himself in order to not reveal that weakness to Professor Quirrell.)

And if the Dark Lord didn't accept his offer...well, then Harry dying would be the least of his worries.

"My magical power iss esssentially without limit. Will not tell you how, am not willing to rissk that you could duplicate the effect. However, I am willing to demonsstrate ass you require. Inflamare."

The ground around them was fire, the air around them was fire, everything turned to red in that torrent of flame...

"Aguamenti."

A wall of water descending, a vast cloud of steam rising.

"Evanesco."

No more water, no more steam, no more fire, just the Boy-who-Lived and the Dark Lord standing across from one another.

"And how do you think this will kill me? I have horcruxess, many of them, sspread acrosss the world! You cannot find me, cannot kill me! Thiss is meaninglesss!"

"Do not need to find you."

"What?"

Harry felt sick. This felt too wrong, this was against everything he knew, everything he believed in, everything he wanted, but there was no other way he had been able to find.

"With Aguamenti I can create great quantitiess of water, far beyond what you just ssaw if necesssary. With Arresto Momentum I can move it as I wish, direct it into the Ssun."

"You sseek to put the ssun out?" Harry didn't know why, but the voice sounded, somehow, almost afraid.

"No, that's not what will happen." Harry had read a blog post about it when he was young, about what would happen if you pointed a giant hose at the Sun. "More water will make Ssun hotter, not colder. Hotter, and hotter, and hotter, until eventually it will explode. Ssupernova, it iss called."

Those eyes looked different now, somehow, looked like they had fear in them. Harry pressed onwards.

"Such amazing things we Muggles have learned. How stars are born, how they are preserved from death, how they die. And it had never even occurred to me to consider that such knowledge might be dangerous. Thank you for that, Professor."

"Not enough, boy! You know that I have horcruxed sspacecraft, that..."

Harry shook his head. "Heard once of a way to calculate how much energy is releassed by a ssupernova. Take any number you pleasse, and then make it bigger. It will reach out far enough to vaporize the Pioneer probe and all other human-launched spacecraft. I do not know if that will be enough - it iss mundane force still, iss posssible it cannot affect magical items - but you have taught me ssomething that will."

Harry raised the wand, traced a rune in the air.

"Thank you alsso for sshowing me that, Professsor. With a Penssieve it iss posssible to review memoriess, watch over and over again until I have learned what I musst. Now, even if Horcruxesss sshould ssurvive, I can reach them all eassily with my power, desstroy with Fiendfyre until nothing iss left of you."

The Dark Lord's face seemed almost panicked...and then, suddenly, it was cold again, controlled if not calm.

"Well done, boy. You have gained power sufficient to kill me indeed...but what of your world?" The hand came up, gestured around. "You claim you would reduce all of this to fire, just to kill me?"

"Only if you do not meet my demandss."

"No. That is ssimply untrue, boy. I would believe that you had found a way to lie in Parsseltongue before I believed you would do that. A fine bluff, perhapss, but nothing more. If you wissh to claim to me that there iss ssomething of you that I do not know, if there iss ssome reasson that you would act in complete disscord with everything I have ever sseen of you, then convince me of it now."

And this was a very good point. It was one that Harry's mind had been fighting over for much of this past week. But then he had discovered something that had brought him, if not peace, then at least a kind of grim resolve. Harry raised his wand in a trembling hand and spoke, pouring in power from his limitless reserves, to cast the spell more powerfully than its creator had ever imagined it could be used...

"Vitalis Revelio."

Above them, in the sky, like the sparkling lights of stars only somehow warmer and brighter, little points of red, glowing faint against the bright sky of daytime.

A whole galaxy, a whole universe, worlds beyond count, with light and beauty and happiness of their own.

And to unleash Lord Voldemort on them could not be allowed to happen.

Harry had spoken to people, not many were willing to talk about it but he'd found a few who were, and he'd found out more than he wanted to know about the Cruciatus Curse.

And he had realized something.

He wasn't afraid enough of it.

Because it didn't look scary. You pointed a wand at someone and said 'Crucio', and they screamed. The Emperor had done something worse-looking to Luke in Star Wars, which Harry had watched when he was six and which hadn't particularly bothered him.

If you imagined having the Cruciatus Curse cast on yourself, versus imagining having yourself strapped down and your fingernails slowly ripped out one by one with a pair of pliers, the second one felt much scarier. It felt terrifying and visceral and real in a way that the simple movement of a wand did not.

But there was a reason Lord Voldemort had used the Cruciatus curse to torture people with, to threaten people with, to threaten their families with.

It was because it was worse.

And to unleash this Dark Lord, who thought in terms of pain and sorrow and misery, who would take any action to achieve his ends, not with hatred for others but with simple disregard that managed to be infinitely worse, who thought that an attachment to another person was simply an invitation for them to be tortured as leverage over you, who wanted to tear apart the human race and remake it in his image...

To unleash that upon this flawed, weak, pathetic, broken, beautiful, bright universe was something Harry simply would not allow to happen.

And if that meant the end for him, if that meant the end for everyone he had ever known, if that meant a flash of light that wiped a planet from the galaxy as if it had never been...

He would pay that price.

It was a terrible thing to say, he knew. A terrible thing to do, a terrible thing even to risk.

But when you considered a universe where the Dark Lord rode out from Earth at the head of an army of monsters forged in his image, with the full power of Magic unlocked and ready to heed his call, with a cold darkness that would take everything beautiful in this universe and tear it apart towards his will to power, and then you considered a universe where a single star blazed bright in the heavens and then went out...

There really wasn't any contest.

The Boy-who-Lived faced the Dark Lord, and around them the world spun, one Earth amidst the stars, one Sun shining bright in the darkness, two Riddles standing beneath it, one with eyes of red who would save the world to destroy the universe, and one with eyes of green who would destroy the world to save the universe.

For it is the most common failing of moralists, that they assume the world is fair and good and nice, that they assume there must be a good option as opposed to two bad ones, that they think if you simply don't do anything wrong everything will turn out all right. And sometimes, when the world is warm and bright and man lives in luxury wrought by his hands and his mind, that might even be true.

But when the world is dark and cold, and man is huddled tight in a cave while the beasts roar outside, the only thing he has that can drive back the dark is fire.

THE END